<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some modest reflections upon the commitment of the Earl of Shaftsbury, arising from the late indictment against Mr. Stephen Colledge</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13153401</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13153401</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 751:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some modest reflections upon the commitment of the Earl of Shaftsbury, arising from the late indictment against Mr. Stephen Colledge</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>July 12, 1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, 1621-1683.</term>
               <term>Colledge, Stephen, 1635?-1681.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:98124:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Some modeſt Reflections upon the Commitment of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> ariſing from the late Indictment againſt Mr. <hi>Stephen Colledge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TIS long ſince we were aſſured by thoſe to whom we owe intire Credit, that had the Papiſts ſucceeded in their Deſign of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the King, 1678. the Diſſenters, and ſuch others as they propoſed to regiſter and inroll in that number, were to have been charged with the Guilt of that Divelliſh and Traiterous Aſſaſſination: But it pleaſed God, through a timely diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Helliſh Conſpiracy, not only happily to preſerve his Majeſties Life, but to deliver many thouſand innocent Perſons from the Capital dangers, into which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Party had contriv'd to have brought them, by a falſe and ſcandalous Accuſation. And therefore finding the Nation not only awakened to preſerve it ſelf by all due and Loyal ways, but juſtly provok'd to bring upon them the puniſhments which they had deſerved by that Helliſh Plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſon of the King, the eſtabliſhed Government, our Religion, and the Lives of all true Proteſtants; they have been indeavouring ſince, by all the Arts and Induſtry they could, partly to Corrupt the Witneſſes that had diſcovered their Villanies, and depoſed againſt them, and partly to oblige them, and ſuch other profligate Perſons as they could hire and ſuborn, to ſwear a Sham-Plot, wherein his Majeſties beſt and moſt Loyal Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould be reported to be ingaged. And though they have been detected in above twenty ſeveral Inſtances of this kind, and thereupon diſſappointed as to the ends which they propoſed unto themſelves; yet having <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other Game which they can play with any probability of ſucceſs, they h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ued this Deſign with the more indefatigableneſs, and having employed <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Policy to mould it into ſome credible form, they have been at great <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vaſt expence to bribe needy and debauch'd Fellows to ſupport and confirm it by horrid and unpreſidented Perjuries. For they ſuppoſe, that could they but get one Proteſtant to be found Guilty upon ſuch an Indictment as they have been providing and framing matter for, they ſhould then be able to involve a great many under the Suſpition of the ſame Guilt. And conſequently, ſhould the King come to be Aſſaſſinated by ſome Popiſh Hand, they would labour to render Proteſtants obnoxious to the ſcandal of having perpetrated ſo abominable a Crime. However, by ſuggeſting to his Majeſty, that His Proteſtant Subjects are embark'd in a Conſpiracy againſt His Perſon; they do promiſe themſelves to bring the King either to truſt and rely upon them for His ſafety, or to grant an Act of Univerſal <hi>Oblivion</hi> for the quieting the minds of His People, and the peace of His Government. Or the leaſt that they do hope from this pretended <hi>Plot,</hi> is, That the ſame Perſons being produced as Witneſſes in this Caſe, that had appeared to give Evidence concerning the <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> they ſhall come to be diſ-believed in reference to the one, through their not obtaining Credit in relation to the other. But as I ſhall as preſent decline the Conſideration of thoſe Reaſons, why theſe very Witneſſes ought to be believed in whatſoever they have Sworn againſt the Papiſts; though no Faith or Credit are to be given unto what they depoſe againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, ſo I conceive the Papal Party may happen to exclude themſelves from having any ſhare in an Act of <hi>Indemnity.</hi> by being the Authors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of this <hi>Sham</hi> Conſpiracy, whereby they would ruin ſo many of the chief upholders of the Eſtabliſhed Government, and the Reformed Religion. Nor can there be a greater Evidence that the Popiſh Plot is as effectually carried on as ever, than this late attempt to render His Majeſty jealous of His moſt Loyal Subjects, and to cauſe them to be diſtruſtful of Him, and thereby render Him and them naked of all Defence againſt the manifold preparations they have made both at home and abroad, for the deſtroying of His Perſon, and the Subverſion of the Government.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98124:2"/>
            <p> It is beyond all contradiction out of whoſe <hi>Forge</hi> this <hi>Engine</hi> to endanger our Peace, and deſtroy many Innocent Proteſtants came; ſeeing it appears by the Teſtimony of good and ſubſtantial Witneſſes, that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> had not only notice of, but divulged it to ſuch as they converſed with abroad, before there was any ſuſpect or apprehenſion of it here. For there are ſeveral now in Town who were not only told beyond Sea, about the 27th and 28th of <hi>June,</hi> that my Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and divers others would be ſecured before the ſaid Perſons could arrive in <hi>England;</hi> but the <hi>Prieſts</hi> who were the Authors of this unto them, openly declared that they expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch ſucceſs in their projections and undertakings from it, as to be able to ſay Maſs in our <hi>Churches</hi> at <hi>London</hi> before <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> next. Nor was it only in <hi>Flanders,</hi> where the <hi>Fathers</hi> and thoſe they had intruſted this ſecret unto were acquainted with it; but we underſtand the ſame by ſome lately come through <hi>France,</hi> who alſo heard from the like hands, that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and many other Proteſtant Lords were to be committed, before the moſt Inquiſitive and Sagacious here, could entertain a thought that there was any ſuch thing intended.</p>
            <p>But it is eaſier for men acted by rage and malice, to frame and contrive a Deſign whereby to ruine others, than to make it coherent in the parts of it, or give it that Face and Colour which may render it probable. And as no man that knowes the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> will think that ever he could enter into ſuch a Conſpiracy as he is charged with, much leſs can they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Perſons of ſo mean Fortunes and ſhallow underſtandings as hitherto are accuſed for it ſhould not only be acquainted with, but have the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal promoting of it committed unto them. For tho' Mr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> and Mr. <hi>Colledge</hi> may be men very well qualified for their reſpective Employments, of great zeal for the Proteſtant Intereſt, and the legal Rights of the People, and of good reputation for their Integrity, yet they are not Perſons of thoſe Abilities, Eſtates or Power in their Country, as to be preferred before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> above them in underſtanding, as well as in all other reſpects, to be conſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d adviſed with about the regulation or change of the Government.</p>
            <p>But <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e apply our ſelves to conſider the nature and quality of this Plot, as we <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>et into it, and have it a little unveiled by the <hi>Indictment</hi> preferred againſt Mr. <hi>Stephen Colledge</hi> on <hi>Fryday</hi> laſt, we ſhall go near to find this Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Conſpiracy, that ſome have made ſuch a noiſe about, to be the moſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous and <hi>Romantick</hi> Invention that ever men pretending to wit or ſenſe ſuffered to be impoſed upon their belief. For by <hi>Colledges</hi> being introduced by one of the Witneſſes reviling the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> in terms as groſs and opprobrious as falſe, all that know the Man are ſufficiently inſtructed what little truth there is in all the reſt whereof he is accuſed. For there is none in the world that he hath that known eſteem for, and in whoſe ſervice in conſiſtency with his Loyalty to his Prince, he would ſo ſoon ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice himſelf and all that he hath, as the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Monmouth.</hi> And ſo far do all men judge him from uſing ſuch ignominious expreſſions as he is accuſed of concerning that great Perſonage, that they verily think had any of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes uſed that Language of his Grace in <hi>Colledges</hi> hearing, he would have taught him better manners, though with the hazard of his life. But the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> are ſo accuſtomed to aſperſe and ſlander this <hi>Duke</hi> in the moſt ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Terms, that they cannot forbear the fathering baſe and reproachful Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies of him upon ſuch who would not forgive themſelves the Crime of having a low or diminiſhing thought concerning him. But the Deſign of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this accuſed perſon ſpeak thus vilifyingly of his <hi>Grace,</hi> is too obvious not to be diſcerned, and ſo ſilly that every Apprentice Youth laughs at it. The Popiſh Party finding that the Duke is ſincerely and unchangably fixed for the Proteſtant Religion; and that thereupon he hath a great and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved room in the hearts of all true <hi>Engliſhmen;</hi> they would fain endeavour to perſwade him that the People do deſpiſe and ſcorn him, thinking that if any thing could, this would make him leſs Zealous for the Proteſtant Doctrine and Worſhip. But they will find themſelves deceived; for as nothing can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate his love to the Eſtabliſhed Religion, ſo the extraordinary reſpect which the People do Univerſally bear him upon this account is neither to be leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards nor alienated from him. But when we advance a ſtep further,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98124:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>and find this pretended Plot to be no leſs than a National Conſpiracy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a Prince whom they ſo unanimouſly reſtored to the Throne of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors a few years ago, we ſhall find cauſe to disbelieve every word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it; and to pity the folly and ſimplicity of thoſe that have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to abuſe his Majeſty, and his Miniſters with ſo ill contrived a Sham. For according to the Evidence which <hi>Smith</hi> and others gave in Court, it is no leſs than a Plot, wherein not only <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> but the very <hi>Parliament</hi> are all embark't and engaged. But as the naming and intereſting the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a Conſpiracy, is enough to ſatisfie any reaſonable man that there is none at all; ſo it enlightens us upon what Motive and Inducement all this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and contrived. For the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> knowing the Villanies which they are Guilty of, and being ſenſible of the Dangers they are lyable unto from the Juſtice of a <hi>Parliament</hi> whenſoever one meets and continues to ſit; they have therefore no other courſe to ſteer, but to render <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſuſpected to his Majeſty, that he may call no more. Accordingly after they had hired a company of raſcally ſcriblers to deſame <hi>Parliaments,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons;</hi> they now aſſume the impudence openly to arraign them of a Treaſonable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Depoſing the King and altering the Government. But the fellowes whom they had ſuborned to this purpoſe, tho' they had the Villany to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſtruments in ſo black an undertaking, yet they had not the wit to conceal it till it was ripe to be vented and improved. For beſides that one had the boldneſs in a late Pamphlet <hi>to adviſe the King to reign Arbitrarily, Smith</hi> that famous Witneſs is known to have given out ſome time ago that <hi>he would ſpoil our Parliaments.</hi> But the ſuffering Mercinary Perſons to ſpeak and write of Parliaments with that Impunity they have done of late; is enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and betray the whole project and deſign to every rational man. And can any one think that if there were ſuch a Conſpiracy wherein ſo many Perſons of Quality, Power and Eſtates were engaged; that his Majeſties Guards would be able to prevent their executing whatſoever they intended? Or can any man imagin that it is for the Kings ſafety and Intereſt, to have the generality of his People brought to believe that he entertains ſuch an opinion of them, as that they are United in a Conſpiracy againſt his Perſon and Government? Were not the King ſafe through the room that he enjoys in the hearts of his People, and did not they apprehend themſelves protected by their own Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; what <hi>Smith</hi> ſaid in the Face of ſo great an Aſſembly as was at the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> laſt, and with ſo much impudence, that it plainly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be ſpoken upon Deſign, were enough to blow up the Peace of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to throw us into blood in four and twenty hours.</p>
            <p>But the place where this Plot of ſeiſing the King was to have been Executed; does further aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, that all this is meer Fiction and <hi>Romance,</hi> and that there was no ſuch thing ever thought of. For as it was impoſſible that any number of Men proportionable to ſuch an undertaking could go to <hi>Oxford</hi> without being ſeen and obſerved, ſo it is very well known, that the Town was much emptier than could have been expected, conſidering that together with the whole Court, the great Council of the Kingdom was there Aſſembled. And inſtead of the Members being accompanied with a Train ſuitable to ſuch a Deſign they denied themſelves the having thoſe menial Servants, with which they are uſually attended elſe where. 'Tis true that ſome Gentlemen were honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the company of their Friends ſome part of the way thither; but it is as true that the Perſons who paid them that reſpect, returned quietly to their Habitations, after they had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged that piece of Civility, which they owed their Repreſentatives. And whereas it was Sworn, that they rode Arm'd and with led Horſes, and that this was in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to apprehend the King; I ſhall take the liberty to ſay, that the Perſon who made ſuch an Inference deſerved a <hi>Reprimand</hi> in the open Court Shall the Witneſs <hi>Smith</hi> ride out of Town accompanied with two Servants <hi>martially</hi> accoutred with <hi>Fuſees</hi> and Piſtols, as he did on <hi>Sunday</hi> laſt? And ſhall not Lords, Knights and the beſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in the Kingdom be allowed to travel with a Sumpter Horſe, and a man or two with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, but there muſt be a Conſpiracy to deſtroy the Government? But though ſome men have both loſt their Diſcretion, and made Shipwrack of their honeſty, in obtruding ſo falſe and nonſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical a Story upon the Nation; yet are thoſe whoſe Wit and Underſtanding have not ſo far forſaken them, but that they can ſee through all this, and whoſe Integrity will guide and oblige them to judge impartially. For is it to be apprehended that they could entertain a purpoſe of ſeiſing the King at <hi>Oxford,</hi> who were ſo afraid of venturing themſelves thither, and ſo importunate with His Majeſty, that the Parliament might have ſat at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! inſtead of harbouring any thoughts of attempting upon the King, or others, they were apprehenſive that the Papiſts had ſome deſign to be Executed there againſt them.</p>
            <p>Was it ever known, that when a Conſpiracy was ſo univerſally laid, as this is ſaid to have been, and wherein ſo many were concerned, as are reported to have been engaged in this, that Men would loſe the only opportunity of Executing what they had intended, knowing withall the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to which they were lyable ſhould they be diſcovered, and how impoſſible it would be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98124:3"/>to conceal a buſineſs of ſo high and dangerous Nature, with which ſo many were made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And can there be any thing more incredible, than that there ſhould have been ſuch a Plot againſt His Majeſty at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and yet that there ſhould never appear the leaſt <hi>Symptom</hi> or Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage of it, neither during the ſitting of Parliament, nor at, or after their Diſſolution: Yea was not His Majeſty ſo ſurrounded with armed Forces, beſides His having the whole <hi>Militia</hi> and <hi>Poſſe</hi> of the Shire in Hands that he could truſt, that the Noble-men, and Gentlemen who are fancied to have been in this Conſpiracy, bearing no proportion unto them, the very thought of ſuch a thing as is impoſed upon them, would have argued them <hi>Lunatick</hi> and Diſtracted. But what Villains were theſe Witneſſes, if they knew of ſuch a Deſign, that they did not acquaint His Majeſty with it, before He expos'd His Perſon to ſo eminent a hazzard. Or how comes it if the King and his Miniſters knew it, that it hath lain dormant ſo long ſince. For beſides the great danger to which they muſt be believed to have ſuffered His Perſon and the Government to have been all this while expoſed, if they were informed of ſuch a Plot ſo long ago; this one thing had been a more juſtifiable reaſon of the ſpeedy diſmiſſing that Parliament, than all that are in the Declaration which was publiſhed upon that occaſion. 'Tis true, Mr. <hi>David Fitz-Gerrald</hi> ſpake of ſuch a deſign the Night after the Parliament was Diſſolved, with this further Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, That the City of <hi>London</hi> was in Arms. and that his Majeſty would have been Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, had he not eſcaped in that haſte which he did. But as the falſity of one part of this ſcandalous Suggeſtion ſhews of what Mettal and Stamp all the reſt is, ſo no Man had more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to rejoyce in the Parliaments being Diſſolved, than this Footman <hi>Metamorphoſed</hi> of late into a Gentleman of Quality and Eſtate. For had the Houſe ſat on that <hi>Monday</hi> to hear the Cauſe which was depending before them againſt him, he had been made appear to be the moſt Infamous Perſon alive, and more worthy of being ſent to ſome place, provided for recolving the worſt of Men, than to be allowed to frequent the Palaces of publick Miniſters, and the Houſes of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrators of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But if we enquire into the quality of the Witneſſes, and conſider not only the probabilities, but the Demonſtrative Evidences of their having been tampered with, we ſhall be yet more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced, that there neither is, nor ever was any ſuch Plot as the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> ſtands Committed for. And to Wave the Conſideration of the ſeveral Crimes with which all of them are Chargeable, and for which ſome of them have been Indicted and Arraigned, I ſhall inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome other <hi>Topicks,</hi> which it may be more convenient at preſent to Diſcourſe of. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place no ſmall Inducement to think that they have been ſubborned, that it can be proved upon all of them, and that by many Perſons and thoſe of as good Reputation as any in and about the City; that they have often declared, even ſince the <hi>Oxford</hi> Parliament, that they never knew of any Presbyterian Plot, nor of any Conſpiracy, wherein ſo much as one Proteſtant was engaged. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> it contributes ſomething to raiſe in us the ſame Perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they delivered their Teſtimony, as if it had been conſigned to them to get by heart, and not as a Depoſition relating to words, which they had heard in occaſional Diſcourſe ſome time ſince, and which they were to call over with that fear and modeſty, which became Perſons that were liable to miſtake and forget. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Garbe which they are lately gotten into, and the plenty of Money that their Pockets are filled with, increaſeth the belief that they have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by ſome one or other to ſay what they do, and that they are well pay'd and rewarded for it.</p>
            <p>For ſome of them that were lately in Debt beyond any probability of being ever able to pay what they owed, have within theſe few days found Money both to diſcharge their Creditors, and new vamp themſelves. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It creates a ſhrewd ſuſpition how theſe Perſons came to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as Evidence for the proof of a Proteſtant Plot; that divers others, as will appear in due time by their own Depoſitions, have been tempted to be ſerviceable in the ſame Deſign. <hi>Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> that all this is <hi>ſham,</hi> and proceeds from Subornation is evident beyond all control; in that ſame of the ſix Witneſſes who were muſtered up at the <hi>Old-Baily</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> laſt, after they had ſworn ſuch and ſuch things in the Face of the Court; acknowledged to the Grand-Jury when the were Examined one by one, that they were hired unto it, and that they had a ſum of Money for doing of it. Which as it vindicates the Integrity of the Jury in returning <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus</hi> upon the <hi>Bill;</hi> ſo it intimates unto us upon what Reaſons ſome whom I forbear to name, oppoſed their being Examined apart. For as all the perſons who ſerved in that Jury are men of that known honeſty and uprightneſs, that they would not willfully Perjure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſave a Kingdom; ſo moſt of them are not only avowed Members of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but two at this very time <hi>Church Wardens,</hi> and a third of them an <hi>Officer</hi> in the <hi>Reformed Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> of the City. But it being hop'd that they will give the World an account of the Juſtice of their own Verdict, I ſhall leave what may be further ſaid in the Vindication of it to themſelves.</p>
            <p>But what will it amount unto towards the proof of a Proteſtant Plot, wherein my Lord of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and many other Great and worthy Perſons are ſaid to be concerned; if ſome raſh and unadviſed words ſhould be proved againſt <hi>Colledge</hi> and <hi>Whitaker.</hi> Shall other men, and thoſe the beſt and wiſeſt in the Nation, under his Majeſty, be immediately judged Traitors, becauſe one or two warm and inconſiderate perſons have talk't fooliſhly and extravagantly. We are fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrange World, if a Body of men muſt be made accountable for the giddineſs of ſome, and thoſe ſuch as they had little converſe with. Nor are the <hi>Phanaticks</hi> to be reproached for the unwary and Dangerous expreſſions of theſe Perſons, ſeeing they are not only Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but chargable with ſome failures, that the Diſſenting Churches would not allow any to continue in their Communion that ſhould be found Guilty of them.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall leave the further purſuit of this at the preſent, and only add that the ſame day that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> was committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> there was a Warrant obtain'd of His Majeſty to the Privy Seal, for the pardoning three <hi>Oneals</hi> that are known Traitors. Which as it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates how much His Majeſty is ſolicited by ſome ill men, ſo this ought to be recorded for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he commanded the ſtopping of their Pardon as ſoon as he underſtood what they were.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily, July</hi> 12, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
